About 15 years ago, I went to visit a friend in Hong Kong.
Hace 15 años, fui a visitar a un amigo en Hong Kong.
And at the time I was very superstitious.
En esa época yo era muy supersticioso.
So, upon landing -- this was still at the old Hong Kong airport
Así que, al aterrizar -- todavía en el antiguo aeropuerto de Hong Kong
that's Kai Tak, when it was smack in the middle of the city --
llamado Kai Tak, cuando estaba justo en medio de la ciudad --
I thought, "If I see something good, I'm going to have a great time here in
-- pensé: Si veo algo bueno, me lo voy a pasar muy bien aquí
my two weeks. And if I see something negative, I'm going to be miserable, indeed."
estas dos semanas. Y si veo algo negativo, va ser un desastre.
So the plane landed in between the buildings
Así que el avión aterrizó entre los edificios
and got to a full stop in front of this little billboard.
y se detiene frente a este pequeño cartel.
(Laughter)
(Risas)
And I actually went to see some of the design companies
Y de hecho fui a ver algunas de las compañias de diseño
in Hong Kong in my stay there.
en Hong Kong durante mi estancia
And it turned out that --
y resultó que --
I just went to see, you know, what they are doing in Hong Kong. But I actually walked away with a great job offer.
sólo fui para ver, ya saben, que están haciendo en Hong Kong. Pero de hecho me fui con una gran oferte de trabajo.
And I flew back to Austria, packed my bags,
Y volví a Austria, hice mis maletas.
and, another week later, I was again on my way to Hong Kong
Y, una semana más tarde, estaba de vuelta en Hong Kong
still superstitions and thinking, "Well, if that 'Winner' billboard is still up,
todavía supersticioso y pensando: Bueno, si todavía está esa cartelera de "Winner" (ganador)
I'm going to have a good time working here.
Lo voy a pasar muy bien trabajando aquí.
(Laughter)
(Risas)
But if it's gone, it's going to be really miserable and stressful." So it turned out that not only was the billboard still up
Pero si no está, va a ser estresante y un desastre. Así que resultó que no solo el cartel todavía seguía ahí
but they had put this one right next to it.
sino que habían puesto éste al lado.
(Laughter)
(Risas)
On the other hand, it also taught me where superstition gets me
Por otro lado, ésto me enseñó a dónde me lleva la superstición
because I really had a terrible time in Hong Kong.
porque realmente lo pasé fatal en Hong Kong.
(Laughter)
(Risas)
However, I did have a number of real moments of happiness in my life --
De todos modos, tuve varios momentos de verdadera felicidad en mi vida --
of, you know, I think what the conference brochure refers to
-- de, ya saben, creo que el folleto de la conferencia se refiere a
as "moments that take your breath away."
momentos que te quitan la respiración.
And since I'm a big list maker, I actually listed them all.
Y como soy muy bueno haciendo listas, los puse a todos en una.
(Laughter)
(Risas)
Now, you don't have to go through the trouble of reading them
Ahora, no es necesario que se tomen la molestia de leerlo
and I won't read them for you.
y yo no lo voy a leer para ustedes.
I know that it's incredibly boring to hear about other people's happinesses.
Ya sé lo verdaderamente aburrido que es escuchar sobre la felicidad de otras personas.
(Laughter)
(Risas)
What I did do, though is, I actually looked at them from a design standpoint
Lo que hice, sin embargo, es mirarlos desde el punto de vista del diseño
and just eliminated all the ones that had nothing to do with design.
y eliminé aquellos que no tenían nada que ver con el diseño.
And, very surprisingly, over half of them had, actually, something to do with design.
Y, para mi sorpresa, alrededor de la mitad de ellos, tenían relación con el diseño.
So there are, of course, two different possibilities.
Así que hay, por supuesto, dos opciones.
There's one from a consumer's point of view --
Hay uno desde el punto de vista del consumidor --
where I was happy while experiencing design.
-- en el que soy feliz mientras experimento el diseño.
And I'll just give you one example. I had gotten my first Walkman.
Y les daré un ejemplo. Había recibido mi primer Walkman.
This is 1983.
En 1983.
My brother had this great Yamaha motorcycle
Mi hermano tenía su gran moto Yamaha
that he was willing to borrow to me freely.
que estaba dispuesto a prestarme libremente.
And The Police's "Synchronicity"
Y el casete de "Synchronicity" de Police
cassette had just been released
que justo acababa de salir
and there was no helmet law in my hometown of Bregenz.
y no había ninguna ley para usar casco en mi pueblo natal de Bregenz.
So you could drive up into the mountains
Así que podía conducir por las montañas
freely blasting The Police on the new Sony Walkman.
disfrutando libremente a The Police en el nuevo Sony Walkman.
(Laughter)
(Risas)
And I remember it as a true moment of happiness.
Y lo recuerdo como un momento de felicidad.
You know, of course, they are related to this combination of
Por supuesto que éstos están relacionados en una combinación
at least two of them being, you know, design objects.
de al menos dos objetos de diseño.
And, you know, there's a scale of happiness when you talk about in design
Y, ya saben, existe una escala de felicidad cuando hablamos de diseño
but the motorcycle incident would definitely be, you know,
pero el incidente con la moto estaría, ya saben
situated somewhere here -- right in there between Delight and Bliss.
situado en algun lugar aquí -- entre Placer y Dicha.
Now, there is the other part, from a designer's standpoint --
Ahora, hay otra parte, desde el punto de vista del diseñador --
if you're happy while actually doing it. And one way to see how happy designers are when they're designing could be to
-- si eres feliz cuando lo estas haciéndolo. Y una manera de ver cómo de feliz están los diseñadores cuando diseñan podría ser,
look at the authors' photos on the back of their monographs?
¿mirar a las fotos en la parte de atrás de sus monografías?
(Laughter)
(Risas)
So, according to this, the Australians and the Japanese
Así que, según esto, los australianos y los japoneses
as well as the Mexicans
al igual que los mejicanos
are very happy. (Laughter)
son muy felices. (Risas)
While, somewhat, the Spaniards ...
Mientras que, de algún modo, los españoles
and, I think, particularly, the Swiss
... y, en mi opinión, especialmente los suizos
(Laughter),
(Risas)
don't seem to be doing all that well.
no la están pasando tan bien.
Last November, a museum opened in Tokyo called The Mori Museum,
El pasado Noviembre se inaguró un museo en Tokyo, llamado Museo Mori
in a skyscraper, up on the 56th floor.
en un rascacielos, arriba en el piso 56.
And their inaugural exhibit was called "Happiness."
Y su exposición inagural se llamaba "Felicidad".
And I went, very eagerly, to see it, because --
Y fui muy emocionado a verla porque --
well, also, with an eye on this conference.
Bueno, estaba ya pensando en esta conferencia.
And they interestingly sectioned the exhibit off into four different areas.
Y muy curiosamente la exhibición estaba separada en cuatro áreas.
Under "Arcadia," they showed things like this, from the Edo period --
Bajo "Arcadia" mostraban cosas como ésta, del periodo Edo --
a hundred ways to write "happiness" in different forms. Or they had this apple by Yoko Ono -- that, of course, later on
-- cien maneras distintas de escribir "felicidad". O tenían esta manzana de Yoko Ono -- que, por supuesto, más tarde
was, you know, made into the label for The Beatles.
se convertiría en el sello para The Beatles.
Under "Nirvana" they showed this Constable painting.
Bajo "Nirvana" mostraban este cuadro de Constable.
And there was a little -- an interesting theory about abstraction.
Y aquí había una pequeña -- una interesante teoría acerca de la abstracción.
This is a blue field -- it's actually an Yves Klein painting.
Éste es un campo azul -- de hecho es un cuadro de Yves Kline.
And the theory was that if you abstract an image, you really, you know
Y la teoría era, que si se abstrae una imagen, realmente, saben,
open as much room for the un-representable -- and, therefore, you know, are able to involve the viewer more.
se puede abrir un gran espacio para lo irrepresentable -- -- y que por lo tanto, permite al espectador involucrarse más.
Then, under "Desire," they showed these Shunsho paintings -- also from the Edo period -- ink on silk.
Luego, bajo "Deseo", mostraban estas pinturas Shunsho -- también del período Edo -- tinta sobre seda.
And, lastly, under "Harmony," they had this 13th-century mandala from Tibet.
Y por último, bajo "Harmonía", tenían esta mandala del Tibet del siglo 13.
Now, what I took away from the exhibit was that
Ahora, lo que me hizo salir de la exhibición fue,
maybe with the exception of the mandala most of the pieces in there were actually about the visualization of happiness
quizás con la exepción de la mandala, la mayoría de las piezas ahí eran sobre de la visualización de la felicidad,
and not about happiness.
no sobre la felicidad.
And I felt a little bit cheated, because the visualization --
Y me sentí un poco engañado, porque la visualización
that's a really easy thing to do.
--es lo realmente fácil de hacer.
And, you know, my studio -- we've done it all the time.
Y, ya saben, mi estudio -- lo hemos hecho todo el tiempo.
This is, you know, a book. A happy dog -- and you take it out, it's an aggressive dog.
Ésto es, ya saben, un libro. Un perro feliz -- y lo haces salir, es un perro agresivo.
It's a happy David Byrne and an angry David Byrne. Or a jazz poster with a happy face and a more aggressive face.
Ésto es un David Bryne feliz y un David Bryne enojado. O un poster de jazz con un rostro feliz y un rosto mas agresivo.
You know, that's not a big deal to accomplish.
Saben, no es un gran logro.
It has gotten to the point where, you know, within advertising
Y se ha llevado al punto donde, uds. saben, en publicidad
or within the movie industry, "happy" has gotten such a bad reputation that
o en la industria del cine, "feliz" se ha ganado tan mala reputación
if you actually want to do something with the subject
que si realmente se quiere hacer algo con el tema
and still appear authentic, you almost would have to, you know,
y aún parecer auténtico, casi hay que, ya saben
do it from a cynical point of view. This is, you know, the movie poster.
hacerlo desde un punto de vista cínico. Ésto es, ya saben, el poster de una película.
Or we, a couple of weeks ago, designed a box set for The Talking Heads
O mi estudio, que diseñamos hace un par de semanas una caja conjunto de "The Talking Heads"
where the happiness visualized on the cover definitely has, very much, a dark side to it.
donde la felicidad que se visualizaba en la cubierta era definitivamente mucho mas oscura.
Much, much more difficult is this, where the designs actually can evoke happiness --
Mucho, bastante más difícil es éste, donde el diseño de hecho puede evocar felicidad.
and I'm going to just show you three that actually did this for me.
Les mostraré tres que, de hecho, lograron este efecto conmigo.
This is a campaign done by a young artist in New York, who calls himself "True."
Ésta es una campaña hecha por un artista joven en Nueva York, que se llama a sí mismo "True" (Verdad).
Everybody who has ridden the New York subway system will be
Todo aquel que haya usado el metro de Nueva York estará
familiar with these signs?
familiarizado con estas señales.
True printed his own version of these signs.
El artista pintó su propia versión de estas señales
Met every Wednesday at a subway stop with 20 of his friends.
Se reunió cada miércoles en una parada del metro con 20 de sus amigos.
They divided up the different subway lines and added their own version.
Dividieron las diferentes líneas del metro y añadiendo su propia versión
(Laughter)
(risas)
So this is one.
Ésta es una.
Now, the way this works in the system is that nobody ever looks at these signs.
Pues, ésto funciona porque nadie nunca mira estas señales.
So you're
Así que
(Laughter)
(risas)
you're really bored in the subway, and you kind of stare at something.
si se está aburrido en el metro, y se mira a algún lugar,
And it takes you a while until it actually --
y tarda un instante hasta que de hecho --
you realize that this says something different than what it normally says. (Laughter)
se entiende que dice algo distinto a lo que normalmente diría. (risas)
I mean, that's, at least, how it made me happy.
Quiero decir, al menos, cómo me hizo feliz.
Now, True is a real humanitarian. He didn't want any of his friends to be arrested,
Ahora, este artista "True" es un humanitario de verdad. No quiso que arrestasen a ninguno de sus amigos,
so he supplied everybody with this fake volunteer card.
así que les dio a todos esta tarjeta falsa de voluntario.
(Laughter) And also gave this fake letter from the MTA to everybody --
(risas) Y también les dio esta carta falsa del AMT --
sort of like pretending that it's an art project
como pretendiendo que es un proyecto artístico
financed by The Metropolitan Transit Authority.
financiado por la Autoridad Metropolitana del Tránsito.
(Laughter)
(risas)
Another New York project.
Otro proyecto de Nueva York.
This is at P.S. 1 -- a sculpture that's basically a square room
Ésto es en P.S. 1 -- una escultura que es básicament un cuarto cuadrado
by James Turrell, that has a retractable ceiling.
de James Turrell, que tiene un techo retraible.
Opens up at dusk and dawn every day.
Se abre al atardecer y al amanecer todos los dias
You don't see the horizon.
No se vé el horizonte,
You're just in there, watching the incredible, subtle changes of color in the sky.
simplemente se está ahi, viendo los increibles, sutiles cambios en el color del cielo.
And the room is truly something to be seen.
El cuarto realmente merece la pena ser visto.
People's demeanor changes when they go in there.
La gente cambia cuando entra ahí
And, for sure, I haven't looked at the sky in the same way
y, tengan claro, no he vuelto a mirar al cielo de la misma manera
after spending an hour in there. There are, of course, more than those three projects that I'm showing here.
después de pasar una hora ahí. Existen, por supuesto, mas que esos tres proyectos que les he mostrado.
I would definitely say that observing Vik Muniz' "Cloud"
Podría decir definitivamente que observando la "Nube" de Vik Muniz
a couple of years ago in Manhattan for sure made me happy, as well.
hace un par de años en Manhattan, me hizo feliz también.
But my last project is, again, from a young designer in New York.
Pero mi último proyecto es, de nuevo, de un joven diseñador de Nueva York.
He's from Korea originally.
Es de origen Koreano.
And he took it upon himself to print 55,000 speech bubbles --
Y se tomó la tarea de imprimir 55.000 burbujas de diálogo
empty speech bubbles stickers, large ones and small ones. And he goes around New York and just puts them, empty as they are, on posters.
-- pegatinas de burbujas de diálogo vacías, grandes y pequeñas. Y va por Nueva York y simplemente las coloca, vacías, en los pósters.
(Laughter)
(risas)
And other people go and fill them in.
Y otras personas las llenan.
This one says, "Please let me die in peace."
Ésta dice: Por favor déjenme morir en paz
(Laughter)
(risas)
I think that was --
Creo que fue --
the most surprising to myself was that the writing was actually so good. This is on a musician poster, that says:
lo más sorprendente para mi fue que lo escrito de hecho estaba muy bien Ésta está en un poster de un músico, que dice:
"I am concerned that my CD will not sell more than 200,000 units
Estoy preocupado de que mi CD no venda más de 200.000 unidades
and that, as a result, my recoupable advance
y que, como consecuencia, el adelanto de la disquera
from my label will be taken from me,
me será arrebatado
after which, my contract will be cancelled,
Después de ello, mi contrato será cancelado
and I'll be back doing Journey covers on Bleecker Street."
y estaré de nuevo haciendo covers de Journey en la Calle Bleecker
(Laughter)
(risas)
I think the reason this works so well is because everybody involved wins.
Creo que la razón por la cual ésto funciona tan bien es que todo el que se involucre gana
Jee gets to have his project;
Jee logra hacer su proyecto;
the public gets a sweeter environment;
el público obtiene un ambiente más agradable;
and different public gets a place to express itself;
y distinto público obtiene un espacio donde expresarse;
and the advertisers finally get somebody to look at their ads.
y los publicistas finalmente logran que alguien mire sus anuncios
(Laughter)
(risas)
Well, there was a question, of course, that was on my mind for a while:
Bueno, había una pregunta, que por supuesto se me quedó en la mente un tiempo:
You know, can I do more of the things that I like doing in design
uds. saben, ¿puedo hacer más cosas de las que me gusta hacer de diseño
and less of the ones that I don't like to be doing?
y menos cosas de las que no me gusta hacer?
Which brought me back to my list making --
Lo que me hizo regresar a mis listas
you know, just to see what I actually like about my job.
-- uds. saben, sólo para ver qué es lo que realmente me gusta de mi trabajo
You know, one is: just working without pressure.
Una es: simplemente trabajar sin presión
Then: working concentrated, without being frazzled.
Luego: trabajar concentrado, sin estar exhausto
Or, as Nancy said before, like really immerse oneself into it.
O, como dijo Nancy antes, realmente sumergirse en ello
Try not to get stuck doing the same thing --
Tratar de no atorarse haciendo la misma cosa --
or try not get stuck behind the computer all day.
-- o tratar de no atorarse en la computadora todo el dia
This is, you know, related to it: getting out of the studio. Then, of course, trying to, you know, work on things
Ésto está, claro, relacionado: salir del estudio Luego, desde luego, tratar de, ya saben, trabajar en cosas
where the content is actually important for me.
donde el contenido sea realmente importante para mi
And being able to enjoy the end results.
Y ser capaz de disfrutar de los resultados
And then I found another list in one of my diaries that actually contained all the things that I thought I learned in my life so far.
Y entonces encuentro otra lista en uno de mis diarios que contenía todas las cosas que pensé que había aprendido hasta ahora en mi vida
And, just about at that time, an Austrian magazine called and asked
Y, casi justo en ese momento, una revista austríaca llamó a preguntar
if we would want to do six spreads -- design six spreads
si quería hacer seis páginas -- diseñar seis páginas
that work like dividing pages between the different chapters in the magazine?
que funcionen como páginas divisorias entre los diferentes capítulos de la revista
And the whole thing just fell together. So I just picked one of the things that I thought I learned --
Y todo el asunto cayó en su lugar Así que simplemente tomé una de las cosas que pensé haber aprendido
in this case, "Everything I do always comes back to me" --
-- en este caso, "Todo lo que hago siempre regresa a mi"
and we made these spreads right out of this.
-- e hicimos estas páginas con referencia a esto
So it was: "Everything
Así que fue: TODO
I do
LO QUE HAGO
always
SIEMPRE
comes
SE
back
VUELVE
to me."
A MI.
A couple of weeks ago, a
Hace una par de semanas, una
(Laughter)
(risas)
French company asked us to design five billboards for them.
compañía francesa nos pidió diseñar cinco carteleras para ellos
Again, we could supply the content for it.
De nuevo, pudimos proveer el contenido
So I just picked another one.
Así que tomamos otra
And this was two weeks ago.
Y esto fue hace dos semanas
We flew to Arizona -- the designer who works with me, and myself --
Volamos a Arizona -- el diseñador que trabaja conmigo y yo --
and photographed this one.
-- y fotografiamos ésta.
So it's: "Trying to look
Así que es : TRATAR DE VERME
good
BIEN
limits
LIMITA
my life."
MI VIDA.
And then we did one more of these. This is, again, for a magazine, dividing pages.
Y luego hicimos una más de éstas De nuevo para una revista, páginas separadoras
This is: "Having" --
Esta es : TENER
this is the same thing;
esto, es lo mismo
it's just, you know, photographed from the side. This is from the front.
-- solo, bueno, lo fotografiamos desde el costado Ésta desde el frente
Then it's: "guts."
y es: AGALLAS
Again, it's the same thing -- "guts" is just the same room, reworked.
De nuevo, es la misma cosa -- "AGALLAS", solo que vuelto a hacer en el mismo lugar
Then it's: "always works out."
y luego: SIEMPRE FUNCIONA
Then it's "for," with the light on.
y luego "PARA" con la luz encendida
(Laughter) And it's "me."
(risas) y este soy "MI".
Thank you so much.
Muchas gracias
(Applause)
(Aplauso)